Gildersleeve-Du Congé collection, Inclusive: circa 1910, 1916-1918, Bulk: 1916
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
Gildersleeve-Du Congé collection
Inclusive: circa 1910, 1916-1918, Bulk: 1916
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
1149
Gildersleeve, Fred A, 1880 - 1958
3 document boxes.
The Gildersleeve-Du Congé collection includes plate glass negatives of photographs taken in and around Waco, Texas, by noted photographer Fred A. Gildersleeve.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Average.
Biography/Profile
Born in New Orleans, Louisiana, on 1909 April, 9 Oscar Norbert DuCongé was the first African-American mayor of Waco, Texas, serving from 1974-1975. Additionally, he served as a Waco city councilman in 1972 and was an avid volunteer in the community up to his death on July 26, 1978.
Former Waco Mayor, Roger Conger, received the extensive collection of Waco photographer Fred A. Gildersleeve some time after his death. The subject matter of the photo negatives contained in this collection were either requested by DuCongé or selected by Conger to present as a gift.
Fred A. Gildersleeve, whose work comprises this entire collection, was born on 1880 June 30, and came to Waco in 1905 living here until his death in 1958. During most of this time he documented important aspects of the city's history, life, culture, and events. Additionally, he is one of Waco’s best-known photographers being commissioned by local businesses, residents, Baylor University, and the African-American Paul Quinn College, the latter of which the bulk of the Gildersleeve-DuCongé Collection represents.
Paul Quinn College was originally started in Austin, TX., in 1872, as the Connectional High School and Institute for Negro Youth. When the school moved to Waco in 1877 on 8th and Mary Streets, it was known as Waco College and taught trades such as blacksmithing, carpentry, and tanning to newly freed slaves. It became Paul Quinn College in 1881 named after Bishop William Paul Quinn, the fourth Bishop of the African Methodist Episcopal Church. It was then relocated to Elm Street in east Waco on 20 acres of land that was once part of the Garrison Plantation.
In 1952 December, Paul Quinn Colleges’ girl’s dormitory was destroyed by fire. The following year in 1953 May, the campus was affected by a devastating tornado that tore away roofs and caused widespread damage to the entire campus. This same tornado destroyed a large part of downtown Waco and killed a total of 114 people. However, by 1954, the African Methodist Episcopal Church came to the aid of Paul Quinn College and paid off their debts and additionally funded the construction of the $150,000 Gomez Administration Building. In 1954, the Waco Chamber of Commerce launched a successful community wide campaign and raised $100,000 for the construction of a new girls dormitory to replace the one destroyed by fire.
In 1964, Waco businessmen helped aid Paul Quinn College in the construction of the Sherman-Abington Library that could house 30,000 volumes. In 1968, a women’s dormitory, Lucy Hughes Hall, and a men’s dormitory, Richard Allen Hall, were both constructed partly from a grant through the Moody Foundation. In 1967, Paul Quinn College earned further funding under the “Model Cities” program. Waco earned this designation at a time when the community was almost ten years into a wide scale federal Urban Renewal program.
In 1968, Paul Quinn College was the only four-year institution in the city’s targeted redevelopment area for the “Model Cities” program. Additionally, the college received funds from Baylor University and Texas State Technical Institute in a cooperative project due to its location in a “Model Cities” redevelopment section of Waco. All of this work had greatly benefitted the institution and by 1972, its 100th anniversary, the Paul Quinn College campus and facilities were valued at 2 million dollars.
By 1979, the operating budget of the college was 2.5 million dollars and operated on funding by the African Methodist Episcopal Church, United Negro College Fund, federal funding, and private donations. In 1990, Paul Quinn College moved to Dallas, TX. Currently still in operation, the institution is the oldest liberal arts college for African-Americans in the state of Texas. The former campus located at 1020 Elm Avenue is now occupied by the Rapaport Academy Quinn Campus Middle School and the Meyer High School.
Scope and Content
The Gildersleeve-Du Congé collection includes a variety of glass plate negatives. Twelve of the negatives are of Paul Quinn College in Waco, Texas, taken in 1916. Two are of Waco Chamber of Commerce Agriculture showing scenes of a gentleman with crops in circa 1918. One negative is of Waco’s New Hope Baptist Church choir and orchestra, circa 1910, and one negative is of a desk and office belonging to a Mr. L.S. Henry of Anderson & Co., Waco, Tx. The Paul Quinn College images are of students, staff, and classes within the school; there are interior shots of classes in session, exterior and interior group shots, and students working with their equipment and supplies.
Arrangement
The seventeen 8x10 inch glass-plate negatives in this collection are arranged in 2 series. They are: Series I: Paul Quinn College and Series II: General.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 1149. Acquired 1975-02-27
Related Resources
Related references
Kelley, Dayton, ed. The Handbook of Waco and McLennan County, Texas. Waco: Texian Press, 1972.
Match Their Faith, Paul Quinn Building Drive, 1872-1972. Pamphlet. Waco Chamber of Commerce, Waco, Tx.
"Paul Quinn College Centennial, 1872-1972." Waco Tribune-Herald, 1972 March 5, Section G, 6.
Index Terms
Subjects (Organizations)
Paul Quinn College -- History.
Places
Texas -- Race relations.; Waco (Tex.) -- History -- 20th Century.
Subjects
African American -- Texas -- Waco -- Politics and government.; African American college students -- Texas -- Waco -- History.; African Americans -- Segregation -- Texas -- Waco.; Race relations -- Texas -- Waco -- History.; Universities and colleges -- Texas -- Waco -- History.
Genres
Negatives (Photographs)
- Paul Quinn College, 1; This series contains 13 negatives of Paul Quinn College.
  Administrative Information
  - Waco-Paul Quinn College-2266, 1916 (Box 1, Item 1)
  - Waco-Paul Quinn College-2267, 1916 (Box 1, Item 2)
  - Waco-Paul Quinn College-2268, 1916 (Box 1, Item 3)
  - Waco-Paul Quinn College-2269, 1916 (Box 1, Item 4)
  - Waco-Paul Quinn College-2270, 1916 (Box 1, Item 5)
  - Waco-Paul Quinn College-2271, 1916 (Box 1, Item 6)
  - Waco-Paul Quinn College-2272, 1916 (Box 2, Item 7)
  - Waco-Paul Quinn College-2273, 1916 (Box 2, Item 8)
  - Waco-Paul Quinn College-2274, 1916 (Box 2, Item 9)
  - Waco-Paul Quinn College-2275, 1916 (Box 2, Item 10)
  - Waco-Paul Quinn College-2276, 1916 (Box 2, Item 11)
  - Waco-Paul Quinn College-2277, 1916 (Box 2, Item 12)
  - Waco-Paul Quinn College-2279, 1916 (Box 3, Item 13)
- General, 2; This series contains 4, 8x10 glass plate negatives. They are scenes relating to the Waco Chamber of Commerce, Waco New Hope Baptist Church choir and orchestra, and the desk of L.S. Henry.
  - Waco Chamber of Commerce: Agriculture-3262, undated (Box 3, Item 14)
  - Waco-Chamber of Commerce: Agriculture-3266, undated (Box 3, Item 15)
  - Waco-Henry, L.S. Desk-899, undated (Box 3, Item 16)
  - Waco-New Hope Baptist Church, Choir and Orchestra (George S. Conner, director) 658, undated (Box 3, Item 17)